<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ichthyothēra, or, The royal trade of fishing discovering the inestimable profit the Hollanders have made thereof, with the vast emolument and advantages that will redound to His Sacred Majesty and his three kingdomes by the improvement of it : now seasonably published by command for the benefit of the nation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45976</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12210012</idno>
  <idno type="VID">56259</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248556951</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing I31</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16408</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12210012</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45976)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56259)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 764:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ichthyothēra, or, The royal trade of fishing discovering the inestimable profit the Hollanders have made thereof, with the vast emolument and advantages that will redound to His Sacred Majesty and his three kingdomes by the improvement of it : now seasonably published by command for the benefit of the nation.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 8, 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.F. for R. Royston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Contains (8 p. at beginning): [Letters patent appointing a "Council of the royal fishing of Great Britain and Ireland", and providing for the regulation of the fishing industry] London : Printed by John Bill and Christopher Barker, 1661.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Fish trade --  England.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Fish trade --  Netherlands.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56259:1"/>
            <p>ΙΧΘΥΟΘΗΡΑ, OR, The Royal Trade OF FISHING. DISCOVERING The inestimable Profit the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> have made thereof, with the vast Emolument and Advantages that will redound to his Sacred <hi>Majesty</hi> and his three Kingdomes by the Improvement of it.</p>
            <p>Now seasonably published by Command for the Benefit of the Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. F.</hi> for <hi>R. Royston</hi> Bookseller to his most Sacred MAJESTY, MDCLXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:56259:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56259:2"/>
            <head>NI SOIT QVI MAL Y ENSE DIEV ET MON DROIT</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES</hi> the Second, by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To all to whom these presents shall come greeting. Know ye that We out of Our Princely Care, tending as well to the Publike Weal of Our Kingdoms, as the private Commodity of Our Subjects, have diligently looked into and observed the great plenty of Fish, wherewith the Seas, Estuaries or Inlets, Greeks, Arms of the Sea, publike Rivers, Nooks and Lakes of Our Dominions, and the Ines thereunto belonging, by the blessing of Almighty God doth abound; and how great profits unto Our Subjects, and increase of strength unto Our Sea Forces, as well in times of War as Peace, may from thence arise; what an ease it will
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56259:3"/>be to Our Kingdoms, to have Lazie and Idle people set on Work, and Crained up in the Trade of Fishing, whereby they may be able to relieve themselves, and how much Merchandize and Traffick may by their industry be improved; And having also with the Advice of the Council of Our Kingdom, weighed as well the publike as private Commodity, and all other consequences thereof, if Our Subjects shall diligently, seriously, and effectually employ their care and poins to the use and improvement of Fishing; And for other urgent Reasons and Causes Vs thereunto mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, Have nomniated and constituted, and by these presents, We do make, constitute, ordain and appoint, Our dearest and most entrely beloved Brother, <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and our right Trusty and right welbeloved Cousins and Counsellors, <hi>Edward</hi> Earl of <hi>Clarendon</hi> Our high Chancellor of <hi>England, Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi>Southampton</hi> Our high Treasurer of <hi>England,</hi> and likewise Our right trusty and right welbeloved Councellor <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Roberts</hi> Lord Privy Seal, and also Our right trusty and right welbeloved Counsin <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Richmond</hi> and <hi>Lenox,</hi> and Our right trusty and right welbeloved Cousins and Councellors <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle</hi> Lord General of all Our Forces, <hi>Iames</hi> Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> Lord Steward of Our Houshold, <hi>Henry</hi> Marguis <hi>Dorchester, Mountague</hi> Earl of <hi>Lyndsey</hi> Lord great Chamberlain of <hi>England,</hi> and also Our right trusty and right welbeloved Cousin and Counsellor <hi>Edward</hi> Earl of <hi>Manchester</hi> Lord Chamberlain of Our Houshold, and also Our right trusty and welbeloved Cousin <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>brey</hi> Earl of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and Our right trusty and right welbeloved Cousin and Counsellor <hi>Algernon</hi> Earl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and also Our trusty and right welbeloved Cousins, <hi>William,</hi> Earl of <hi>Bedford, Philip</hi> Earl of <hi>Pembroke</hi> and <hi>Montgomery, Theophiles</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:56259:3"/>Earl of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> and also Our right trusty and right welbeloved Cousin and Councellor <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Leicester,</hi> and also Our trusty and right welbeloved Cousins <hi>Iames</hi> Earl of <hi>Suffolke, Iames</hi> Earl of <hi>Marleborough, Ierome</hi> Earl of <hi>Portland,</hi> and also Our right trusty and right welbeloved Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sins and Councellors <hi>George</hi> Earl of <hi>Norwich, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> Earle of <hi>Sandwich, Arthur</hi> Earl of <hi>Anglesey,</hi> and also Our trusty and right welbeloved <hi>George</hi> Lord <hi>Berkley</hi> of <hi>Berkley, Francis</hi> Lord <hi>Willoughby</hi> of <hi>Parham, William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven, Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Berkley</hi> of <hi>Straiton,</hi> and also Our right trusty and right welbeloved Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor <hi>Denzill</hi> Lord <hi>Hollis, Frederick</hi> Lord <hi>Cornewallis</hi> Treasurer of Our Houshold, and also Our trusty and right welbeloved <hi>Horace</hi> Lord <hi>Townesend,</hi> and also Our right trusty and welbeloved Councellors <hi>Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Ashley,</hi> Sir <hi>Charles Berkley</hi> Knight, Comptroller of Our Houshold, Sir <hi>George Carterer</hi> Knight, Vice-Chamberlain of Our Houshold, Sir <hi>Edward Nicholas</hi> Knight, one of Our principal Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries of State, Sir <hi>VVilliam Morice</hi> Knight, another of Our principal Secretaries of State, and likewise Our right trusty and welbeloved Sir <hi>Ieoffry Palmer</hi> Knight and Baroner Our Atturney General, and Sir <hi>Heneage Finch</hi> Knight and Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net Our Sollicitor General, to be the Councel of the Royal-Fishing of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> of which We Our Heirs and Successors will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe ever to be and be called <hi>Protectors;</hi> And we Grant Licence and Liberty that the Council and their Successors for the time being, as oft as to them or any Four of them, it shall seem expedient, may and shall from time to time in such places, meet and make Assemblies, Elect, Constitute, and Depute Officers and Ministers, such as shall be necessary for their service, and consult and debate of the business and affairs of the said Fishing, and make, appoint, ordain and publish Laws, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56259:4"/>and Statutes whatsoever concerning their Ministers, Servants, Fishermen, Mariners, Masters, Factors, and others imployed about the business of the Fishing, and the same as oft as it shall seem necessary to them, Change, Revoke, Correct and Substitute other Ordinances in their stead, and enjoyn pecuniary mulctes or pains of imprisonment to be inflicted according to the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the offence on such as contemn or violate the same, and to new evils arising (wanting amendment) to apply a new remedy fit and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to reason, when and as often as it shall seem expedient to them; yet so as those Laws, Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Statutes be by Vs and Our Heirs ratified and approved before they take force; And also they shall and may in like manner put the said Statutes in due execution, and punish (according to the said Statutes, Laws, and Ordinances, and the tenors of the same) such as contemn and do contrary to them, which Laws, Ordinances and Statutes, We will to be observed in all things, and duely put in execution; yet so as the said Statutes, Laws, Ordinances or Decrees be not derogatory to the Statutes, Laws, Liberties, or Acts of Parliament of Our Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>And We also Will, and by these presents for Vs, Our Heirs and Successors, do grant to the Councel aforesaid and their Successors, that the Fishermen, Mariners, Masters and Servants being in their Fishing business, and to every of them which now are or hereafter shall be attending or imployed in the taking or preserving of Fish, be from time to time hereafter free from all Pleas or Plaints in any the Courts or Seats of Iustice, of Vs Our Heirs or Successors where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, for any thing concerning the Fishing business while they are attending the taking or preservation of Fish, so as none of them shall or may
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56259:4"/>answer before any Iustices, or Stewards, Bailiffs, or Iudges of the Courts and Seats of Iustice, or Vs or Our Heirs or Successors, for any Trespass, or Contracts touching the Fishing business, but before the Councel aforesaid, nor shall give over Fishing or their Fishing works upon the summons of any of the Ministers of Vs, Our Heirs or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, but only upon the summons of some Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers or Ministers of the said Councel, or of the Iudges to be Delegated by the said Councel; and for the better Government, and to avoid expences, and other charge arising about any the differences that may arise among the Fishermen, Mariners, Masters and Servants belonging to the Fishery, for the speedyer Administration of Iustice, because it may often happen that controversies may arise at Sea between the Fishing Masters, Factors, Mariners and their Servants, to remove which without delay, the Office of Iudge is necessarily requisite, We for Vs, Our Heirs and Successors, do Constitute and Ordain, that in every Province of Our said Kingdoms and Cities in this behalf convenient (to be designed or appointed by the Councel) there be Delegated Iudges under the said Councel; And We also Will that the same Iudges reside and keep Courts in the Burroughs and Cities most convenient for the business of Fishing, to whom we grant full power to make, establish, and publish Laws, Ordinances, and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes temporary, and duly to put them in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, so as the same Statutes and Laws do not repugne nor contradict the Laws, Acts of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, or Statutes of Our Kingdoms, or the Laws or Statutes to be constituted or published by the Councel aforesaid.</p>
            <p>We Will also, and by these presents for Vs, Our Heirs and Successors do grant unto the Councel and their Successors (as well present as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56259:5"/>to come) that none of their Fishermen, Ministers nor Servants, neither their Boats, Sloops, Barkes, or Ships, little or great, or of whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Bulk or Burthen they be, nor their Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or furniture, designed or prepared for taking of Fish or Carriage of the same, whether they be in Sea, or in Port, or elsewhere, be Arrested or Impressed for the Service or Imployment of Vs Our Heirs or Successors, or compelled to go in Our Service or Affairs, without the consent of their Owners: And We Will that none of the Fishermen, or any imployed in the taking or preserving of Fish, to be put in Assizes, Iuries, Attaints, Recognizances, or any Inquisition, although they concern Vs, Our Heirs or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, or any others; nor that any of them be against his will made Collector of Tenths, Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenths, Taxes, Tallages, or any other Charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es or Impositions whatsoever, any way granted to Vs, Our Heirs or Successors, nor to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to be Constable or Tything-man against his will.</p>
            <p>And for the better encouragement for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling of all men of Ingenuity to Build Busses, or Fishing Vessels to carry on this Fishing Trade, it is requisite that there should be exected Wharfs, Docks, Storehouses and Granaries about the River of <hi>Thames,</hi> and all the Ports of Our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, where the conveniency will be most advantagious for the Work, for the accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of all those that shall set out the said Vessels to the Fishing Ground, to receive their Provisions of Salt, Clapboard, Hemp, and Vessels, their Rigging and Provisions, and the Nets (which the poor set on Work, shall make) thereto be Tanned and fitted up accordingly, which to effect will require many thousand pounds, and cannot be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ocured but by way of Lottery, and by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56259:5"/>Letters Patents for a Collection in all Parishes within Our Dominions: We do by these presents, Give, Grant and Licence unto the Councel aforesaid, for the setting up of a Lottery within Our Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> for the space of three years as King <hi>Iames</hi> of blessed memory did grant for the Plantation of <hi>Virginia</hi> in the year <hi>1612.</hi> And also, Letters Patents for a free Collection in the Churches, giving it in charge to the Ministers to evidence the goodness of the Work, as the Council shall direct, unto whom it is referred; and what Monies shall be so raised, shall be paid unto Our right trusty and welbeloved Cousin <hi>Philip</hi> Earl of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> and by him to be issued out for the execting of Wharfs, Docks, Store-houses and Granaries aforesaid, with the consent of the aforesaid Councel or any four of them.</p>
            <p>And also We do hereby grant, that for the space of seven years, from the first entrance into the Trade of Fishing, all the Returns made for the sale of the Fish, either in the Baltick Seas, <hi>Denmark, Norway</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> shall pay no Customes inwards nor outwards, and shall freely vend their Fish in Foreign Parts, and make the returns thereof in the Commodities of the place, without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption, by Power or Vertue of any Charter whatsoever to the contrary; And all Victuallers, Inns, Alehouses, Taverns, Coffee-houses and the like, shall take <hi>1, 2, 3, 4.</hi> or more Barrels of Herrings yearly, at the price of Thirty shillings <hi>per</hi> Barrel, untill Foreign vent be attained to perfection, according as the Councel shall order the same; And all Barrels of Pickled Herrings and Codfish, that shall be brought into Our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by the <hi>Flemings</hi> or others, shall pay two shillings six pence <hi>per</hi> Barrel to the Stock of that place or Port where they shall vend the same, which shall be also ordered by the Councel afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:56259:6"/>
            <p> And further by these presents, We do Order that all Pickled Herrings and Barrel Codd taken by the Fishing Busses and Vessels of Our Nation, when it is to be exported to Foreign Parts, shall give a Bill of Entry of the quantity, and quality, and place whether it is to be exported, unto the Officers that shall be appointed thereunto by the Councel, their Commissioners or Agents appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and also the returns made, whereby a due account may be kept yearly to be exhibited to Our Lord Treasurer for the time being.</p>
            <p>And whereas in case of breach of Peace with any Foreign Nation (which God forbid) We are graciously pleased, and do hereby promise and grant, that the said hers shall be protected in their Fishing Grounds, and shall have Convoys for their exportation; And all other Priviledges and Immunities shall be granted unto them in future, as experience shall discover, for the better carrying on this business of Our Royal Fishing. In witness whereof We have caused these Our Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to be made Patents, Witness Our Self at <hi>VVestminster</hi> the Two and Twenty day of <hi>August,</hi> in the Thirteenth year of Our Raign.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>John Bill</hi> and <hi>Christopher Barker,</hi> Printer's to the KING'S most Excellent Majesty. 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56259:6"/>
            <head>ΙΧΘΥΟΘΗΡΑ, Or, THE ROYAL TRADE OF FISHING.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O man is so void of reason as to deny that he is born for the service of God, his Prince, and Country. God requires it for our good; a Prince out of duty derived out of the Command of God; and our Country out of the Law of Nature, next unto our Parents. God directs us out of his written Word, how to serve him; a Prince out of his humane Laws, how to serve and to obey him; and our Country out of an instinct of Nature, how to reverence her.</p>
            <p>The City of <hi>Paris</hi> had a saying of old, <hi>One God, one King, one Faith, one Law.</hi> These four words are effectual, and as much as can be comprehended in our service to God, Prince and Country. <hi>Cicero</hi> saith, <hi>Take away Piety toward God, and take away all communion of Humane Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As most men differ in Feature of Face, in Diet, in Condition and Education; so all good men agree in a unity in the service of God, their Prince, and Country, in their several degrees and stations, the Divine in his Prayers, the Souldier with his Armes,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56259:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56259:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:56259:8"/>Wise men with Counsel, and Rich men with Treasure. This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done willingly, makes sweet Harmony between King and Commonwealth: for that Prince is happy that hath young men to take pains, and old men to counsel; the one doth sustain the other in convenient time (like Fruit, which comes not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor ends altogether) some teaching, and others obeying.</p>
            <p>The next Consideration is, how to make the people subsist in the service of God, Prince, and Country. For there must be a rational means to work by; neither can a Monarchie be upheld and supported without people employed and set on work in their several stations. And therefore considering that God created man (as is aforesaid) for the service of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, his King, and Country, and that every one is bound to employ himself in the service of them, and to prefer them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all private Respects; let me follow that Maxim, as the meanest of many thousands of other of his <hi>Majestie</hi>'s Subjects, and offer my Mite as the first-fruit of my Harvest, not like the Divine, the Souldier, the Wise man, nor the Rich man that I spake of; but with my poor Talent God hath endued me with (which is my Experience) that could not have been compassed if God had not given me a longer life then many others; if with that life he had not marvelously defended me from Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of Enemies, the Sword, Water and many other Casualties which mankind are subject to. If also with those daies and years he had not given me a desire and means to observe, conferre, and be inquisitive, I had not been able to preferre this my desire to serve my King and Country, but I should have gone as naked out of the world and void of experience as I came naked into it.</p>
            <p>Let not the odious name of <hi>Projector</hi> prejudicate your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, for what I propound deserves not that title. There is no burthen that the invention of lend brains can invent to vex the Commonwealth with, but they style it by the name of a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> pretending a fair face under a soul vizour. The difference betwixt them and me is this: I have no end but for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good of the Kingdome; I neither exact nor expect gaine; I treat of no new-devised Tax or Toiles; I invent no Impositions,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56259:8"/>nor raise Contributions; I inforce no man to undertake, nor compel people to adventure; I perswade out of Reason, that the beginning of my Propositions may be examined, that the end may be approved, and Counsel may be taken of the Wise: then I doubt not my undertaking shall be acceptable, all men satisfied, every man enriched, and my Prince and Country strengthned, feared and admired.</p>
            <p>My meaning is not to leave our fruitful Soile untilled, our Seas unfrequented, our Ilands unpeopled, or seek remote and strange Countries uninhabited, and uncivil barbarous <hi>Indians,</hi> where nothing appears to us but wood, earth and water upon our first Arrival; for all other hopes must depend upon our labours, upon costly expences, upon the adventure of the Sea, upon the honesty of Undertakers; and all at last to produce nothing but <hi>Tobacco,</hi> a new invented needless Weed, as by the use and custome of it appears.</p>
            <p>In what I propound I will not direct you to the Eloquence of Books to perswade, to the inventing Wits to intice, to the affecting Traveller to encourage, nor to any man that with fair words may abuse you: you shall know as much as I can say by casting a Hook into the Seas; and by example of one Line and Net, you may conjecture, by multiplication, the profit that will arise by the work; you shall be made to know, how that though you be born in an Iland seated in the Ocean, reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished with abundance of all sorts of Fish swimming from one Shore to another, yet your experience hath not taught you the Profit, nor hitherto inspired you with the Benefits and Blessings that may arise from that Fish, the principallest of all commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. I doubt not but to give you that light therein, that you shall confess your selves heretofore blinded, and be willing to blow from you the mist that hath been an impediment to your sight: you shall be awaked out of your drowzy sleep, and rouse your selves to farther this the best business that ever was presented to <hi>England</hi> or King thereof, nay, I will be bold to say to any State seated in the world; I will not except the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the West-<hi>Indies</hi> by <hi>Columbus,</hi> an act of great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56259:9"/>of great Profit, and that hath wrought the greatest effect to the <hi>Spanish</hi> Nation.</p>
            <p>YOu will wonder, that being born Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> and casting your eyes only upon the gainful soile of the Land, you should never yet conceive what the Sea afforded. I confesse it were impossible for you to live in that Ignorance, if it did not appear by the ensuing discourse how you, your Country, and especially the Princes of these Realms have been abused, and the Profit thereof concealed.</p>
            <p>To make my Comparison good between the West-<hi>Indies</hi> and our <hi>English Fishing;</hi> which of them yields most Honour to his <hi>Majesty</hi> and most Profit to his Countries, least danger and least labour to his Subjects, I refer me to your Censures upon my collected Reasons.</p>
            <p>If men consider the Divine work of God, and the end of his working, it is marvellous to behold that <hi>America,</hi> being a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, and able to equal all the rest of the world in bigness, could from the Creation thereof, untill 1490. and odd yeares after the birth of Christ, be concealed from us, and not so much as imagined; though some Philosophers seem to roave at it.</p>
            <p>And when it pleased his Divine Majesty to bestow that Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing upon <hi>Europe,</hi> if we consider the time he did it, and the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of doing it, it will put us into an admiration and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of the power of Christ against the Opinions of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Turks:</hi> for could he shew himself a more just and loving God, then in pouring upon Christendome such Blessings of Wealth at the time it was like to be swallowed up of barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Moores,</hi> who were only withstood by the Wealth of the <hi>Indies?</hi> We may hope the same God hath the same Happinesse in store for this Kingdome, to adde an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Glory to his <hi>Majestie</hi>'s Goodnesse, or else it had been impossible that our loving Neighbours, the industrious <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> should for so many years have enjoyed this <hi>Fishing,</hi> who, to their everlasting Honour and praise, have furnished thereby
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56259:9"/>more Vessels for Sea then all <hi>Europe</hi> besides can muster.</p>
            <p>The first discovery of the <hi>Indies</hi> gave no great hope of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit at the beginning, until after a long painful and chargeable Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation it was brought to perfection. The Fishing upon his <hi>Majestie</hi>'s Coasts of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> needs no Discovery, the experience of our Neighbours hath found it out, and practised it ever since the year 1397. to their unmeasurable Wealth and our shame; and for the honour of him that first found out the pickling Herrings (the which was one <hi>Will. Bachalen</hi> by name) there was erected a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous tombe in the Island of <hi>Biervliet</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> yet to be seen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fishing</hi> produceth more Riches in its way then the other doth, as I will make appear when I come to compute the one with the other.</p>
            <p>The Wealth of the <hi>Indies</hi> is not brought from thence without great expence and hazard, considering the Casualty of the Sea, and the fear of Enemies to intercept it. The <hi>Fishing</hi> is still in view of us and our shoares, our Vessels daily expected in our Harbours, and others ready to ease them of their burthen, and to transport them into other Countries not far remote, where they are in no danger of <hi>Hurricanes,</hi> Enemies, or other perils.</p>
            <p>The assurance of going and coming from the <hi>Indies</hi> may be valued at a great rate; which we shall save in our <hi>Fishing,</hi> there being no fear nor hazard in it.</p>
            <p>The Wealth of the <hi>Indies</hi> being surprised by an Enemy, is more prejudicial to the King of <hi>Spain</hi> then four times that Wealth will profit him, his Enemy being made strong and rich, and he weakned and impoverish'd by it. No such accident can much prejudice us, for in the miscariage of our Fishermen we shall only lose so many Barks, Salt, and Nets, and no Enemy enriched or strengthned by it.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:56259:10"/>
            <p> The planting the <hi>Indies</hi> causeth a scarceness of natural <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> whereby the Kings affairs many times suffer and are at a losse. The <hi>Fishing</hi> employes all our loose people, which abound in this Kingdome, and makes them capable to serve their Prince and Country.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Indies</hi> employ four times more Ships then all the rest of their Dominions, and increase their strength by Sea. The <hi>Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> will maintain twenty Vessels to one of theirs, and <hi>England</hi> may furnish them with most materials belonging unto them, which in time of War are brought into <hi>Spain</hi> with great danger of Enemies.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Indies</hi> are too far remote from <hi>Spain</hi> to be assisted thence if there happen Changes in any part thereof, which other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may take notice of for their advantage. The <hi>Fishing</hi> is one Body governed by a Company that no Enemy can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy; and if Questions arise between parties, they are speedily to be determined without Charge or detriment to either, as the other have their Appeals to their Courts of Justice in <hi>Spain</hi> from the <hi>Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The chief Commodities of the <hi>Indies</hi> are Bullion, Hides, Coch-neale, &amp;c. Our only <hi>Fish</hi> doth countervail them all; and though for the present it affords no Bullion <hi>in Specie,</hi> yet it draws the Money unto it which is coyned of that Bullion.</p>
            <p>The Ships that trade into the <hi>Indies</hi> are great of burthen, and make but one Return or Voiage in a year; and when they are carin'd (for the waters in <hi>Spain</hi> do not rise high enough to ground them) it is done with far greater labour and charge then ours are, that are brought on ground in one ride, and haled off another, ready for a new Voiage, and never want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fraight.</p>
            <p>But what I have observed is not to be accomplished with words, but works, not with talking, but with doing and acting; for betwixt words and deeds there is a great difference, words
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56259:10"/>without deeds and actions are like Water that drowneth people and doth it self no good.</p>
            <p>The property of a Merchant is to have Money in his Purse, and Credit on the Burse, to advance his trade. All men in this work must become Merchants not only for themselves, but for their Prince and Countrey: All are to reap benefit by it, none pain or sorrow but the sloathful, idle, base people, that are like Droans amongst Bees; for the purchase of Sloath is Dispraise.</p>
            <p>There are three things necessary in every work; the Man that works, the Instrument to work withall, and the Matter. There is nothing required of the men in our work but labour and pains: the Instrument to work withall is Ships of several kinds to be made and built: and the Matter to set on work is Money. All these concurring in one will make it a work of Fame, Renown, Strength, Riches, and all the good God can fend unto a Nation and people: but if through sluggishness and careles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, or mistrust of return of Gain, (it being out of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and breeding of Gentlemen, and others that apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to make profit of the Land, and not of the Sea) they neglect the offer and proposal following, we are a people wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be punished with Penury and want, and unworthy to live and enjoy the Blessings of God, which he hath poured upon this Land above all others he hath pleased to create.</p>
            <p>What better Patern can we have in this business then our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and intimate Friends the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> who by their long Travels, their excessive pains, their ingenious Inventions, their incomparable Industry and provident care, have exceeded all other Countreys and Nations in their adventurous Commerces, and made all the world familiar with them by Trade; so that we may justly attribute to them what the <hi>Chineses</hi> assume to themselves, that they only have two Eyes, the <hi>Europeans</hi> but one, all the rest of the people none. How can it better appear then by this; that out of their labours and our <hi>Fish</hi> only, they have increased the number of Vessels as followeth, they have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56259:11"/>fed the world that otherwise would have found a scarcity of food, they have so mightily advanced trading, (and so abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly) that the wealth arising to the Subjects and the Custome to Princes, have shewed them the benefit of it; and lastly, they have so provided for themselves, as that all their people, of what sort soever, though impotent and lame, yet they want not employment, nor are forced to seek out for work for their maintenance.</p>
            <p>And because their quantity of <hi>Fish</hi> is not to be vended in their own Provinces, but dispersed into all parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> I will give you an accompt of it, as it hath been carefully observed, and taken out of the Customers books beyond the Seas.</p>
            <p>In four Towns within the <hi>Sound,</hi> viz. * <hi>Lucenborough, Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Stetin,</hi> and <hi>Dantzick,</hi> they vend in a year between thirty and forty thousand Last of Herrings, which will amount unto more then six hundred and twenty thousand pounds: and we vend none.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Denmark, Norway, Sweden, Liefland, Riga, Revel,</hi> the <hi>Narve,</hi> and other Towns within the <hi>Sound,</hi> there is vended above ten thousand Last, worth one hundred threescore and ten thousand pounds.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> send into <hi>Russia</hi> about one thousand and five hundred Last of Herrings, sold at twenty and seven thousand pounds; and we not above thirty or forty Last.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stoade, Hamburgh, Breme, Emden,</hi> and so up the River of <hi>Elve,</hi> take off in Fish and Herrings above six thousand Last, sold at one hundred thousand pounds; and from us none.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Cleveland, Juliers,</hi> up the River of <hi>Rhene, Franckford, Colen,</hi> and over all <hi>Germany,</hi> in Fish and Herrings they vend near two thousand Last, amounting unto four hundred and forty thousand pounds; and we none.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:56259:11"/>
            <p> In <hi>Gelderland, Artois, Heinault, Brabant, Flaunders,</hi> and the Archduchesse Country, they eight or nine thousand Last, amounting to one hundred threescore and eleven thousand pounds; and we none.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Roan</hi> in <hi>Normandie,</hi> they five thousand Last of Herrings, sold at one hundred thousand pounds; and we not one hundred Last: they are commonly sold for twenty, and sometimes thirty pounds the Last.</p>
            <p>Besides what they spend in <hi>Holland,</hi> and sell there to other Nations, to the value of many a hundred thousand pounds.</p>
            <p>Now having perfected the <hi>Hollander</hi>'s <hi>Fish,</hi> in valuing what they take in our Seas, and vend into forein Countries, our Shame will manifestly appear, that for so many thousand Last of Fish, and so many hundred thousand pounds of money made thereof by them, we cannot give accompt of above one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty Last taken and vended by us.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> are no lesse to be commended for the benefit they make in the Return of <hi>Fish;</hi> for what Commodity soever any Country yields in lieu thereof, they transport in their own Vessels to <hi>Holland,</hi> where they have a continual Staple of all Commodities brought out of the South, and from thence sent into the North and East Countries: the like they doe into the South out of the North, their Ships continually going, and bringing an inestimable Profit, like a weavers shuttle, that he casts from one hand to another, ever in action, till his gain ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the Cloath he makes.</p>
            <p>And if we compare <hi>Holland</hi>'s forecast with ours, the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sloath and Negligence will lye heavy upon us, like him that beats the Bush for another to catch the Bird. For though <hi>Russia</hi> at our Adventure, Charge and Shipwreck was first disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to us, and that for many years it afforded great profit by the constant Trade of eight Ships yearly; yet about twenty years past the <hi>Hollanders</hi> incroached upon us with two Ships, and in continuance of time have brought us to but two or three, and themselves to sixty great Vessels.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:56259:12"/>
            <p> The chiefest gain arising out of our <hi>Fish</hi> and other <hi>English</hi> Commodities they filch from us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>New-found-Land</hi> being an ancient patrimony of <hi>England,</hi> and we the first discoverers thereof, immediately after the finding out of the <hi>West-Indies</hi> by <hi>Columbus,</hi> hath been since a great enriching to the Western parts with the <hi>Fish</hi> there yearly taken. And now the <hi>Hollanders</hi> of late have found the way thither, and sent in the year 1629. twelve or fourteen great Ships to buy up the <hi>Fish</hi> taken by his <hi>Majesties</hi> Subjects; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his <hi>Majesty</hi> doth not only lose his Custome going out (if it had been brought into <hi>England</hi>) but in the Return of that Commodity, which might have amounted unto fourteen or fifteen thousand pounds, if his <hi>Highness</hi> Subjects had had the Carriage of it.</p>
            <p>Not reconing the <hi>Hollanders</hi> principal trading with <hi>England,</hi> there are three Commodities little in shew, and not regarded by us, which they make gain of to themselves: the first is <hi>Lobsters,</hi> the greatest part whereof that finds <hi>London</hi> at the time of the year they bring from the farthest Northern parts of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> never practised by the <hi>English;</hi> the second is the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of <hi>Oysters</hi> yearly transported by them into <hi>Holland,</hi> which causeth the decrease and dearness of Oysters amongst us; the third is the <hi>Lamperns</hi> out of <hi>Thames,</hi> which they use for bait to take their Cod in the North seas, and that makes the scarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and dearnesse of this fish in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the greatest Navigation of theirs, and of most impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance unto their State for maintenance of Ships of burthen and strength, is into the <hi>Streights,</hi> and from the Port of <hi>Marseilles</hi> along the Coast, untill they come to <hi>Venice;</hi> and in this trade I will recon but threescore Ships of two hundred and fifty Tunns each Ship in burthen, leaving more then as many more trading into <hi>Spain, Portugal, Biscay,</hi> and the South part of <hi>France,</hi> and all with our <hi>English</hi> Fish, taken by his <hi>Majesties</hi> Subjects, as namely <hi>Pilchards</hi> caught in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland, Baccalen</hi> in <hi>New-found-Land,</hi> and the red Herrings taken and made at <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:56259:12"/>
            <p> The <hi>Hollanders</hi> do almost intirely enjoy this Trade, what by Comb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nation made with the Merchants that deale in that kind of Fish, and what in the Cheapnesse in the Fraight of their Vessels, which may make them give the better price.</p>
            <p>Within these eighteen years last past they have so increased their Navigation, as that for five ships of ours to one of theirs within the <hi>Streights</hi> before the said eighteeen years, they are able now to muster ten of theirs to one of ours, and merely by this trade of Fish: for true it is that there is not any commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity in the world of so great a bulk and of so small a value, that can set so many Ships of burthen on work.</p>
            <p>As for example, a petty Merchant may fraight his Ship of two hundred and fifty Tunnes, that will not cost above sixteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds, that forty Merchants cannot doe in better Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities. I speak not upon surmise, but what is approved by divers Merchants, and especially one of good accompt, whose name I conceal, unlesse I might have his leave to divulge it. He accounts that by threescore-Ships laden with these three sorts of Fish aforesaid, whereof one peny profit comes not into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and whence they gather the sweet dew of their Food, <hi>Holland</hi> is enriched six hundred twenty one thousand seven hundred and fifty pounds: as I will demonstrate by the worst Commodities brought out of the <hi>Streights.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The principal end I aim at is how to undertake the <hi>Hollanders</hi> at their own weapons, and how to equal them with Pincks and Busses and other Vessels, untill we be made partners with them in Fishing, not by any hostility or uncivil kind of usage, nor to deprive them, by any Prerogative which the laws of Nations cast upon us, or out of envy to their labours to repine at their fortunes, or revenge discourtesies; only we will seek to enjoy what Nature and Nations cast upon us, and make use of our own by the Countenance of our blessed <hi>King,</hi> that in Justice gives all people their right and due. There needs no repetition of my former Narration; Truth hath spoken it, which is so glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of her self, that she needs no false light to give her a better glosse.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:56259:13"/>
            <p> In that which followeth, I will demonstrate the particular proceedings of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> with their Pincks and Busses, with the certain gain they yearly raise out of them: and when it shall appear, and that Experience, the mother of Knowledge, shall make it known to you, I hope you will remember what you are, and how easily you may advantage your selves and Countrey by it.</p>
            <p>I confesse this <hi>Fishing</hi> is a businesse I have long taken into Consideration; my Lord of <hi>Northampten,</hi> if he were now living, were able to witnesse how much it was solicited and desired by me, and no lesse wished and laboured by his Lordship. I caused one <hi>Tobias Gentleman,</hi> a Mariner by profession, but endued with better parts then your ordinary mariners, and much practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the Northern Fishing, to dedicate a book to his Lordship, which gave particular notice of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> proceedings in their Busses and Pincks, and what we should doe in the imitation of them. But by the Death first of my Lord it rested unfollowed, (for some respects) though not unthought on by me, untill the late Duke of <hi>Richmond</hi> revived it, and importuned me once more to it. His Death in like manner made it lye dead, untill his <hi>Majesty</hi> of late, out of his Princely care to the good of his loving Subjects, the Renown of his Kindoms, and desire of the Unity and equal Benefit of his two Realms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> gave it life again, taking more then an ordinary Care for effecting it, well beseeming so blessed and benign a <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I will descend to the particulars of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> Busses, Pincks, Yagers, Lymboats, and the use of them in their several fishings.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>Texell</hi> in <hi>Holland</hi> to the <hi>Brasse Sound</hi> in <hi>Schetland,</hi> (an Island belonging to his <hi>Majesties</hi> Dominions in <hi>Scotland</hi>) it is two hundred and thirty Leagues, whether there resort the 22<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>June</hi> about two thousand Fishing-vessels; the 24<seg rend="sup">th</seg> they put to Sea, being prohibited till then, and a penalty upon the breach thereof, as holding the Herring till then unfit to falt by reason of her fatnesse.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:56259:13"/>
            <p> Every one of these Vessels directs his course to find out the Shoal of Herrings, like the Hound that pursues the Herd of Deer in hunting.</p>
            <p>When they have laden their Busses, which is sooner or later, as they can find the store of Herrings, they presently repair home for <hi>Holland,</hi> and leave their Herrings on shore to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>packed, and from thence immediately to be sent to the <hi>Sound,</hi> where they are received for great Dainties.</p>
            <p>The Busses having thus disburthened themselves in <hi>Holland,</hi> are once more victualled and furnish'd with Salt and Caske, and repair to Sea to look out the Shoal they had formerly left; and then finding them and filling their Busses once again, they doe as they did before, return into <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not ceasing thus, the third time they repair to the Shoal as aforesaid: and in these three Fishings, computing with the least, they take to the number of one hundred Last of Herrings, which being valued but at ten pounds the Last, will amount unto one thousand pounds.</p>
            <p>Many times this Fishing-fleet is attended with certain Ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels called Yagers, which bring Salt, Caske and Victuals, to truck with the Busses for their Herrings, and carrie them directly into the <hi>Sound</hi> as aforesaid, without returning home; for it is a matter of great consequence and gain to bring the first Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings into the <hi>Sound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will set down the rate of a Busse new from the stock, with the price of her Nets, Tackling, Salt, Victuals, Caske, mens Wages, and all other Charges whatsoever belonging to her, and will value the profit by the four months Fishing, which may very well continue twenty years, that being the ordinary life of a Busse.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Inprimis, a Busse with her furniture and tackling will cost</hi>—500. <hi>l.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item, a hundred Last of Barrells for three Fishings</hi>— 072.</item>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:56259:14"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item, for Salt</hi>—088.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item, for Beer for four moneths</hi>—042.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item, for Bread</hi>—021.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item, for Bacon and Butter</hi>—018.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item, for Pease</hi>—003.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item, for Billets</hi>—003.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item, for mens Wages for four moneths</hi>—088.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Summa totalis</hi> 835. <hi>l.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Rating the Herrings but at one thousand pounds, there is gotten clear in four moneths five hundred pounds in a Busse, and one hundred threescore and five pounds in money; so the totall summe, as appears, which is gotten is six hundred three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score and five pounds in one Summer; whereout if you deduct one hundred pounds for the weare of the Busse, and the repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Nets against next Summer, yet still there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains five hundred threescore and five pounds for clear gain by one Busse in four moneths in the Summer, which is a greater profit then can be thought to be raised otherwise.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> make the gain of their Busses so certain, that they lay out their Childrens money given them by their deceased Friends in adventures in their Busses; and they have in <hi>Holland</hi> a Treasurie of <hi>Orphans</hi> opened and laid out in adventuring in the Busses.</p>
            <p>Now leaving the Busses, I will shew you the Charge of a Pinck. She being built new, and all things new unto her, will not cost three hundred and threescore pounds, with her Lines and fishing appurtenances.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Inprimis, a Pinck</hi>—260. <hi>l.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item, fifteen Last of Barrels</hi>—010.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item, five weigh of Salt upon Salt</hi>—015.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item, Beer, Bread, Caske, and petty talley</hi>—012.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Item, mens Wages for these two moneths</hi>—020.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Summa totalis</hi> 317. <hi>l.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:56259:14"/>
            <p> Fifteen Last of Barrell-Cod at fourteen pounds and eight shillings the Last, the which is for a Barrell twenty four shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, amounts unto two hundred and sixteen pounds, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out if you deduct fifty seven pounds for the charges in fetting her to Sea, there remains one hundred fifty eight pounds clear gain by one Pinck, with fifteen Last of Fish in two months.</p>
            <p>This Fishing beginneth upon the ending with our Busses, in <hi>November,</hi> and continueth untill <hi>May,</hi> so that they do lade themselves three times in that space.</p>
            <p>I present you with no <hi>Chimeraes</hi> or tumors, toyes to please Children, or with shadows of untruths; for I know Truth to he so noble of it self, that it makes him honorable that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth it, and that an honest man will rather bear witness against his Friend, then obscure truth by a lye. I have disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with what facility the <hi>Hollanders</hi> goe through with this golden Mine of theirs, as they term it in their Proclamation ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. I have proved their Busses and Pincks are built to take Fish; that they fill themselves there in a Summer with Fish; that this Fish is vended, and esteemed as a pretious food, in all parts of <hi>Europe;</hi> and that the Return thereof bringeth them a greater prout then any Commodity whatsoever, without which they could not live. It is manifest that that Fish hath brought them to a great encrease of their strength both by Land and Sea, and of Fame withall, in inabling them to maintain their Warres against so great and potent an Enemy as the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> whom they will not acknowledge.</p>
            <p>I speak not this with an intention to have their Power les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sened, but to shew the great Advantages we lose in not fishing with them, there being Fish enough for them and us.</p>
            <p>And if all these Benefits accrew to them, and nothing but shame to us, let us search into the Cause thereof, and seek to amend it; let us follow their Example, which is better then a Schoolmaster to teach us. Nothing is our bane but Idlenesse, which ingendreth Ignorance, and Ignorance Error; all which we may be taxed with. Nothing is so easy in it self, but to a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56259:15"/>sloathfull man it will prove difficult, if it be done unwillingly.</p>
            <p>There are but two things required to this work; that is to say, a will to undergoe it, and money to goe through with it; which being had, we will plead Charity to begin with our selves, before we yield it to our Neighbours: and then it will soon appear that this businesse may be effected by us with more Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, more Strength, more Renown, more Happinesse, and lesse Expence, then the <hi>Hollanders</hi> have or can goe through it withall. Time is the mother of Experience; and you shall find that time may cure our Carelesnesse past, that Reason could not hitherto doe.</p>
            <p>The Instruments with which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> work, are three Vessels of several kinds, as I have declared; not produced out of their own Countrey, for that yields nothing to farther it but their own pains and labour. Their Wood, Timber and Plancks they fetch out of divers other places. And yet are these of no more availe to undertake their Fishing and Navigation, then Weapons are without hands to fight. For their Iron, Hemp, Cordage, Hops, Barrell, Boards, Mault and Bread, they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to other Countreys, who, if upon any difference they prohibit their transportation, the <hi>Dutch</hi> are to seek a new trade, for their State presently sinketh.</p>
            <p>Upon comparing these Casualties and Inconveniences with ours, you shall discern the advantage and benefit God hath given us more then them: for as to the Materials formerly mentioned that goe to this Shipping, <hi>England</hi> yields most of them, and in little time the Earth may be made to produce them in abundance; so that we shall not need to stand to the Courtesie of Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, or to venture the hazard of the Sea in fetching them.</p>
            <p>Whereas all manner of people, of what degree soever, have commonly an adventure, according to their abilities, in this Fishing of <hi>Holland,</hi> and that the only Exception amongst our selves is want of money to undertake it; you shall understand God and Nature have so provided for us, that I will clearly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56259:15"/>the objection of Money, and throw it wholly upon the Sluggishnesse and ill disposition of our people, who if they will take away the occasion of this imputation, they may take away the offence due to it, and by which we are scandaliz'd.</p>
            <p>The Objection of lack of Money to set on foot this work would seem ridiculous to Strangers, that behold the Wealth and Glory of this Kingdome, with the sumptuous Buildings, the costly insides of Houses, the masse of Plate to deck them, the daily Hospitality, the number of Servants kept to the honour of Masters, and the charitable Almes distributed out of mens su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities: and to descend to more particulars, when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the bravery of Apparel vainly spent, the rich and curious Jewels to adorn their bodies withall, and the needlesse expences yearly wasted, they will conclude, it cannot be <hi>Want,</hi> but want of <hi>Will</hi> that is the impediment. But leaving these obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, let me tell you, there is never a Lord, Knight, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, nor Yeoman of any accompt in <hi>England,</hi> but, if he want Money, is able to furnish either Timber, Iron, Wheat, Mault, Beef, Pork, Bacon, Pease, Butter, Cheese, or home-spun Cloath out of their wool; all which should be received from them at a reasonable rate, and the value allowed them in the adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>No man owneth or hireth Land, but he may as well plant Hemp, to make Lines, Nets and Cordage, seeing the Laws of the Kingdome command it, as any other Grain; which Hemp may be spun by his Neighbours and Tenants, and so all people set on work: then what need have we of Money, but for the building of the Vessels? for you see with what ease every thing else is compassed.</p>
            <p>Before these Busses should direct their Course to <hi>Schetland,</hi> to be there welcomed by the <hi>Hollanders</hi> in their own Houses, I would first take a view of all the Harbours and Creeks capable of Busses in his <hi>Majesties</hi> Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and there design such provision for the advantage of Fishing as shall be requisite. If the <hi>Hollanders</hi> have usually made one<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56259:16"/>thousand pounds in four moneths by three Fishings, we shall be able sure to exceed it in the course following.</p>
            <p>I will suppose our Busses to be at <hi>Brasse Sound</hi> in <hi>Schetland</hi> ready the 24<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>June</hi> to put to sea, in pursuit and chace of the Herring-Shoals; I will suppose likewise that the one and the other have filled their Vessels, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ready on their way to <hi>Holland</hi> to unlade and to return again, as I have said before.</p>
            <p>If you compute their distance, and losse of time in 400. Leagues running forwards and backwards, though the winde favour them both waies, you shall see a great difference of Gain betwixt us and them; for we shall not need to run many Leagues, perhaps not ten, e're we make our next Harbour, where provision shall be made of Victuals, Salt and Caske, and our Busses put their Herrings a-shore to be repacked again, that with all speed they may hasten to sea again in pursuit of the Shoal; and the Herrings being repacked are immediately sent to the <hi>Sound</hi> to take the first Market: all which will be effected before the <hi>Hollanders</hi> can be at home with their Herrings; and yet after they are arrived in <hi>Holland,</hi> they are to saile very near as great a way to the <hi>Sound</hi> as we shall from <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> There needs no argument to prove the truth hereof, seeing a Map will demonstrate it.</p>
            <p>But it may be answered, that the Yagers formerly spoken of, that truck with the Busses for Herrings, will sooner be at the <hi>Sound</hi> then we, and make benefit by the fore-selling of their Fish. To give you satisfaction therein, I pray conceive, our Busses are in Harbour within three hours after they have fished, and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to no foul weather to hurt them; they have a convenience to mend and dry their Nets; they unlade their Herrings and lade their Salt, Caske and Victuals, without interruption, and so goe to sea again speedily: whereas the Yagers must wait their time for fair weather and a smooth sea to change their Salt Victuals and Caske for Herrings; they must watch their time and fit weather to mend any defects in their Nets and Busses, or
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56259:16"/>for drying them. Thus you see all Casualties considered, our Arrival at the <hi>Sound</hi> is more certain, for the Reasons before expressed.</p>
            <p>But there never was any businesse so easy to be accomplished but still found some objection or opposition, till it was made plain and apparent as well to the doubters as beholders: for most men are guided by opinion rather then by Judgement. And so fares it with this hopeful and beneficial Work, for some still frame Reasons and impediments to discourage it; but time will determine the doubt, and clear the mistaking.</p>
            <p>There are three Arguments, or rather Errors, that possesse peoples mindes with the difficultie of our <hi>Fishing,</hi> which I do not mean to convince with bare words, but with infallible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration; for I had better offend in telling truth, then please by feigned falshood.</p>
            <p>The first Exception is, Our taking Fish with greater Charge then the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> by means whereof they will overwork us.</p>
            <p>The second is, That they will doe the same in the Vent and sale thereof, by their long practice in that trade.</p>
            <p>And the third is, The fear of fraud and deceit amongst our selves, as in the President of the <hi>East-Indies, Virginia,</hi> and other Companies lately erected.</p>
            <p>But truth hath no ghostly Father to absolve her, Reason shall make her speak.</p>
            <p>For the first Objection, of our taking Fish with more Charge then <hi>Holland;</hi> you must know, that the Charge belonging to a Fishing-vessel is her Hull, Tackling, Nets, Salt, Caske and Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, the number of Men, and their Wages.</p>
            <p>Butter and Cheese excepted, there are none of the rest of the materials growing in <hi>Holland,</hi> and most of them afforded in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56259:17"/>
               <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> or <hi>Ireland;</hi> by reason whereof <hi>England</hi> may afford them better cheap then <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Victuals used at Sea are Bread, Beer, Flesh and Fish, Butter, Cheese, and Pease. For Fish we may value it at an equal rate, because it costs neither of us any more then the taking. And as Flesh is more chargeable then the rest, so shall it cost us lesse then them, and indeed little or nothing: for it is to be considered, that a fat Beef in the Islands of the <hi>Hebrides</hi> is sold for lesse then twenty shillings, the hide and tallow whereof in <hi>England</hi> will give ten shillings, the other ten shillings will be raised in carrying wine, strong-waters, and other Commodities desired by the people of that Country; for every ten shillings so imployed doubleth the adventure, as namely in <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> ten shillings bestowed in <hi>England</hi> will yield more then the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casse of a Cow.</p>
            <p>For Bread, Beer, Butter, Cheese, and Pease, <hi>England</hi> affords them better cheap then <hi>Holland:</hi> first, in respect they grow in <hi>England</hi> in greater plenty then in <hi>Holland;</hi> secondly, they pay Excise in <hi>Holland,</hi> and not in <hi>England;</hi> and thirdly, no man but knows the difference between the feeding of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and the <hi>English,</hi> and that one <hi>Hollander</hi> eats more then one and a half of our <hi>English</hi>-men at Sea.</p>
            <p>Both the one and the other carries an equall proportion of men, and their Wages are upon an even rate; but herein we shall overwork them for the reasons following.</p>
            <p>In a Busse of fifteen or sixteen men, the meanest whereof hath 20<seg rend="sup">s</seg> the month amongst the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> we will ease the Charge of eight in sixteen, <hi>viz.</hi> we will carry but eight men to the place where we Fish, and we will have eight more for lesse then half the wages we give the rest; and so in a year we shall save in every Busse eight and fourty pounds; by means whereof we shall goe cheaper then the <hi>Hollanders</hi> by nine thousand and six hundred pounds in our two hundred Busses: and moreover, in Wages and Victual for our eight men we shall leave behind us,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56259:17"/>as aforesaid, we shall save as much in Victuals and Wages, so much as in the whole will amount unto eight thousand six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is conceived that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> will transport their Fish at lesse Charge then we, I shall make appear to the contrary. For their Yagers which attend some of their Busses, to carrie their Herrings to the first Market, as I have said, their Herrings are not repacked, but they are allowed more then two Barrels in each Last to make up the tale, by means whereof they pay two Barrells fraight in every Last of Herrings more then we that have the shore to repack; so that 200. Busses will yield us 5000<seg rend="sup">l</seg>. more gain then the <hi>Hollanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas every Fishing-vessel in <hi>Holland</hi> contributes to 20. or 30. men of warr, to defend them from the <hi>Dunkirkers;</hi> our Peace doth ease us of that expence. And this shall suffice in answer to the first, as to the comparison between the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and us in taking our Fish.</p>
            <p>The second point to prove is, That we shall vend our Fish at as easy rates as the <hi>Hollanders.</hi> This your own Experience must needs teach you: for in the <hi>Sound,</hi> where the greatest quantity of Herrings is uttered, as I have before shewed, necessity will compell those Countries to take them off; and it is not their affection to the <hi>Hollanders</hi> above us that will make them refuse ours, to accept of theirs.</p>
            <p>And then consequently, ours will be better sold, in that we shall serve the Market before them, by the means and reasons aforesaid.</p>
            <p>And if we goe farther from home, as to <hi>Spain</hi> or the <hi>Streights,</hi> you must understand that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> Ships goe with fewer men then ours, by reason of the slight building and tackling of their Ships in comparison of ours: and as there is 20. men in 40. difference in the sailing of our Ships, so there is in the strength of them; wherefore the Merchant had better, for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56259:18"/>the safety of his goods, give fifty shillings fraight to us then thirty shillings to the <hi>Hollander,</hi> for his goods shall be better defended from Pirates by our fourty men then their twenty; and the <hi>Hollander</hi> loses many a Ship for want of men to manage them, whereas ours having more men will be the better secured.</p>
            <p>The <hi>English</hi> will double a lee-shoar, when the other will be forced in foul weather upon Rocks; the Cables and Anchors in the <hi>English</hi> will hold, when the other will be forced to come home or break; the <hi>English</hi> will be able to put out saile at sea, when the other must take in; the <hi>English</hi> in some cases may come a-shoar, and by their strength come off again without hurt, when the other will perish: the <hi>English</hi> also draw more water, which keeps them sweet and wholsome in the Sea, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the Merchants goods with little losse; the <hi>Hollander</hi>'s are troublesome and dangerous in a Storm, which causeth great leaking in wine, oyle, and such Commodities, to the great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the Merchant, yea more sometimes then the difference of Fraight comes to.</p>
            <p>As the <hi>English</hi> goe in greater security then the <hi>Hollander,</hi> so shall the Merchant save by not assuring the value of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in Fraight: which I could compute and prove, but it is too tedious. Moreover the <hi>English</hi> having the absolute car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of all the Fish taken by them, as the laws of the Realm do warrant, our Ships shall never want imployment, nor have any cause to look out for Fraights; by reason whereof a Ship of 250. turn may goe cheaper by 200<seg rend="sup">l</seg>. then usually they have done. And thus much for our Forein trade.</p>
            <p>Now let us return to the vending our Fish in the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi> If the Proclamation for observing the daies for Fish be duly kept, it will be one means to vend our Fish, and encourage others to adventure in Fishing; so there be a prohibition, as there is in <hi>Holland,</hi> that no Fish be brought into any of his <hi>Majesties</hi> Kingdomes but by his own Subjects.</p>
            <p>It would not seem a thing unreasonable, to enjoyn every
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56259:18"/>able Yeoman and Farmer in the Kingdome to take a Barrell of Fish for their own spending, considering they save the value thereof in other Victuals, and that it is no other then the Fisher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men will doe to them, to take off their Wheat, Malt, Butter and Cheese, for their food at Sea. The Farmer by this means shall never be unprovided of Fish to observe the daies commanded by his <hi>Majesty</hi> without sending to the Market, as otherwise he will be compelled to doe.</p>
            <p>The Farmer will find by experience that it will be as cheap a food as any other he can feed upon, and give better delight to the tast then any other Victuals of that value, according as it may be in several manners dressed.</p>
            <p>The Labouring-man which works with the Farmer, takes of him his Butter and Cheese; for every poor mans case is not such as to keep a Cow: and such Labourers will be as willing to take Fish of him as any other Victuals, if he be willing to spare it.</p>
            <p>There are few Farmers but spend the quantity of a Barrell of Fish yearly; and he that doth so shall save 20. in the hundred by buying a Barrell together rather then by retaile.</p>
            <p>And that the Country may be better served with Fish and other Commodities then they have been, we will make several staples of Salt, Coals and other Commodities wanted by the Countries, where Boats may passe upon Rivers. As namely, <hi>Middlesex,</hi> part of <hi>Hartfordshire, Surrey, Buckinghamshire, Berkshire</hi> and <hi>Oxfordshire</hi> may be served by the River of <hi>Thames: Essex</hi> may serve it self, part of <hi>Hartfordshire</hi> and part of <hi>Suffolk: Norfolk</hi> will serve <hi>Cambridgeshire,</hi> part of <hi>Suffolk, Bedfordshire, Huntingtonshire, Northamptonshire;</hi> and a staple there made will serve <hi>Warwickshire;</hi> for from thence there goe Carts empty to fetch Coals, which may furnish the Shire with little Charge: <hi>Lincolnshire</hi> will furnish it self, <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinghamshire,</hi> part of <hi>Rutlandshire</hi> and <hi>Darbyshire,</hi> whither the Carts goe empty for Coals out of <hi>Lincolnshire: Yorkshire</hi> will furnish it self, part of <hi>Nottinghamshire,</hi> part of <hi>Rutlandshire</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56259:19"/>
               <hi>Darbyshire</hi> by the <hi>Trent: Cumberland</hi> and <hi>Westmorland</hi> will sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish themselves, both by the West and East Sea.</p>
            <p>Let us leap over the Land to the Western Sea; where <hi>Chester</hi> and <hi>Lancashire</hi> will furnish themselves, part of <hi>Shropshire, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestershire, Staffordshire,</hi> and the North part of <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That side of the Sea will furnish <hi>Wales</hi> till you come to <hi>Severn:</hi> the North side whereof will serve <hi>Pembrokeshire, Carmarthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire, Glamorganshire, Monmouthshire;</hi> and the South part thereof will serve part of <hi>Cornwall, Devonshire</hi> and <hi>Sommerset<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire;</hi> and the River of <hi>Severn Gloucestershire</hi> and <hi>Wiltshire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The South Sea of <hi>England</hi> will furnish <hi>Cornwall, Devonshire, Sommerset, Dorset, Hampshire,</hi> and part of <hi>Wiltshire, Sussex, Kent,</hi> and part of <hi>Surrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus is <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi> circuited. Then consideration is to be had of the meetest places for erecting Staples, to utter the Commodities brought them, and to be received from them.</p>
            <p>If at any time Corn fails the Countries, we will hereafter sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them at a reasonable rate by our trade with <hi>Dantzick;</hi> and if plenty warrant it by the Statute, we will take it off their hands: so that they shall have no cause to complain either of Dearth or Abundance.</p>
            <p>We will provide that no Rogue nor Vagabond shall trouble them, nor the poor of their Parish charge them; for all such people shall be set on work by us: then will the Contributions to the houses of Correction be needless, which will ease their Parishes more then the value of many a Barrell of Herrings they shall take of us comes to.</p>
            <p>When our Staples shall be erected in the Countries, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, out of them we will furnish every parish in the Kingdom with Hemp by weight, to set their people on work, and receive it again by weight, allowing every one such a rate for their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56259:19"/>work as they may well live thereon: no boy or girle of seven years of age, no man or woman how lame of leggs soever, but shall be able to get their livings, no person so blind but may live without Almes; for besides their making of Nets, and such work as goeth thereunto, we will set up the trade of making Cables, and all manner of Ropes, as well to vend abroad, as to furnish the Kingdome at home, as also Poledaves for Sailes, and not be beholding to <hi>France</hi> for them.</p>
            <p>Whereas there are many Yeomen and Farmers which have many Sons that put them to great care how to provide for them out of their mean estates, this Fishing will take off all such youths, make them capable to get their livings, and ease their Parents of their Care and Charge.</p>
            <p>All these Reasons considered, it is apparent that the Farmers and people of the inland Countries, who hetherto have not tasted of this Happinesse, and whose passages by water have not been frequented or known, shall reap as great a benefit and commodity by this Fishing as our selves, and have no more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to refuse the taking of Herrings in the manner aforesaid, then we have to take off the Commodities by which they live. And this shall suffice in Answer to the second Objection, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vending our Fish.</p>
            <p>These six several Trades following we will erect in all parts of <hi>England,</hi> not hetherto practised but in some places near the Sea-side;
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hempsters,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Spinsters,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Carders,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rope-makers,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Weavers of Poledaves,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Net-makers.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In Answer to the third Allegation, of Cousenages and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits amongst our selves, as it is in the <hi>East-Indie, Virginie,</hi> and other Companies; first, I cannot say, whether they deserve that imputation of Fraud which is cast upon them, yea or no, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port is like an echo, heard, but no man knows where: but to give satisfaction in the managing of our Trade that no deceit
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56259:20"/>can creep in at it, that which followeth shall declare it.</p>
            <p>It is not intended that a select Company shall have the dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the Fishing, as in those other cases they have; or that they shall receive, disburse, or imploy the Moneys of the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers, or direct and order things at their pleasure; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwise, (for example) whosoever shall be a member of ours, it shall be at his choice what to adventure, with whom to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, and the way how to adventure, without control of any other: as thus, If one undertake for a Busse or a Ship, it shall be in his power or choice to accept of a partner, two, or three, or more, and after the value of their adventures, they shall set forth as many Ships as they please, and appoint such persons for the ordering of their affairs as they shall make choice of; so that if any deceit be, it shall be among themselves, for no body else shall meddle with their Adventure.</p>
            <p>But because in all Commonwealths there must be a Head to govern, and execute Justice, to which the rest of the Body must submit; it is convenient that the supreme Commission and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority should be given to the Lords of his <hi>Majesties</hi> most Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Privy Councel, and other persons of quality, to be chosen as well in the Kingdoms of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> as in <hi>England,</hi> to settle a form of Government, and to provide for eschewing of all mischiefs and other inconveniences that may fall out betwixt man and man, and prevent abuses, and questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that may arise betwixt Merchants, Mariners, owners of Ships, Salters, and others that it may concern: but these Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners are no waies to handle or meddle with the parties in their Adventures, or with their stocks of Moneys, or with imployment of them.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, to stop the mouths of such suspicious conceits of Cousenage, you will find that it is not within the wit of man to over-reach one: for the quantity of Fish which a Busse takes cannot be hid, because of necessity she must repair to the Coasts of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> where the Customer enters every Barrell of Fish in his Book, and none can be transported
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56259:20"/>without a Cocquet. The number of Cask which they pay for, they will look that they be filled; the people that goe in them are able to justifie how much they take; and lastly, according to the quantity of your Salt, you are to expect the number of Barrels: the price of those that are vended at home as well as those abroad is easily estimated; the usual fraight of Ships and the Factorage is easily guessed at; and therefore no means left for Deceit.</p>
            <p>Now to return once more to the <hi>Fishing,</hi> where we left the Busses for the Summer, to provide against the first of <hi>December,</hi> to repair to the Island of <hi>Lewis;</hi> where untill the beginning of <hi>February</hi> they shall take the best Herrings of all, in Loughs and Creeks, as I have before declared: about the first of <hi>March</hi> we shall depart from thence to the Island of <hi>Roane,</hi> some forty miles from <hi>Lewis,</hi> from whence there runs a Bank 100. miles in length, as far as <hi>Tilley-head</hi> in <hi>Ireland;</hi> which Bank affordeth the best Cod and Ling of any part of the Seas.</p>
            <p>Betwixt the first of <hi>March,</hi> as I said, and the twentieth of <hi>June,</hi> the time that I assign for repair to <hi>Brasse Sound</hi> in <hi>Schet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> I make acount they will fill their Busses 3. times with Cod and Ling, and leave them at the Island of <hi>Lewis,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause there is never a Harbour in <hi>Roane;</hi> from whence they shall be fetched by other Vessels, which shall bring Salt and other necessaries for the Island and Fishing. The 20<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>June</hi> once approaching, the Busses are to repair to <hi>Brasse Sound,</hi> as in the year before, and prosecute the Fish and Herrings, till they arrive at <hi>Yarmouth.</hi> And if they then please to take an account of the year spent, it will appear that one Busse im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by us, as I have projected, will be of much more value to us, then any one to the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> and we shall learn the way how his <hi>Majesties</hi> Dominions may flourish, not for a little while, but for ever.</p>
            <p>Now will I stand over for the Islands of <hi>Orkney</hi> and <hi>Schetland,</hi> which need no other description, but that it is pity so good and civil people should inhabit no better a Countrey. We may
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56259:21"/>say the contrary of them that we may of those of the Islands of <hi>Hebrides,</hi> that it is a good land, but a bad people; these are good people, but their soile barren.</p>
            <p>The way to relieve them is, humbly to beseech his <hi>Majesty</hi> to accept of his Revenues in <hi>Orkney</hi> and <hi>Schetland</hi> in Fish, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the people of those Islands to undertake and practise the way of fishing, which through poverty and want of trading they are not able to goe through withall.</p>
            <p>Besides the Rent they shall pay to his <hi>Majesty</hi> in Fish, what they take more we will buy of them, and supply them with Salt, Nets, Hooks, Boats, or what else they shall need; by which means every man in those Islands shall be able to subsist and maintain themselves, who know not now how to live, but are brought up in Sloth and Idlenesse.</p>
            <div type="proposals">
               <head>Proposals for the better inhabiting of the Island of <hi>Lewis</hi> and other Islands adjacent.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THat his <hi>Majesty</hi> be pleased to call in the Patent of late granted to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> for inhabiting the <hi>Lewis,</hi> where they are crept in of purpose to set up a Fishing on that Coast, to defeat his <hi>Majesties</hi> Subjects of that benefit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That his <hi>Majestie</hi> grant Immunities to his Subjects of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> to inhabit there, and erect Towns, Villages, Store-houses, and all manner of Manufactories and Trades, so that hereafter we need not to supply those Islands, but shall find there all things to our hands, as in other places of <hi>Europe</hi> where Trades are upheld and maintained.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That his <hi>Majesty</hi> do constitute a Governour to be there resident for the space of three years, and not to exceed that time, lest in longer continuance abuses should creep in by the Avarice of Governors.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:56259:21"/> 4. That in every Island there be erected one principal Town above the rest, and a Cittadell in it to keep the people in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; for naturally the Inhabitants of those Islands are incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Incivility, Treachery, and love of Liberty, which are next neighbours to Rebellion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That every Child be taught the <hi>English</hi> or <hi>Scotch</hi> tongue, and that their educations be according to their abilities of body and disposition of mind, some in Learning, and some in manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and husbanding of ground; but the most part in Fishing and Sea-affairs, as having so convenient a seat for the same.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That the native inhabitants of those Islands hold no Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondency with the <hi>Highlanders</hi> upon the main Continent more then is needfull, considering the danger that may ensue by their too great familiarity, they being naturally the most dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and worst people of all his <hi>Majesties</hi> Dominions: and that there be a special care, that they marry one with another in the Island, or with the <hi>English</hi> or <hi>Scotch,</hi> and in any case to prohibit all marriage betwixt them and the <hi>Highlanders,</hi> as aforesaid.</p>
               <p>I Have annexed hereunto, as you see, what I think fitting to be put in present execution for planting the Islands of <hi>Hebrides;</hi> which being done, all the good mentioned before will follow upon it, besides other things which I forbear to touch, as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of State, and too high for me to meddle with.</p>
               <p>I have at length brought my intention to an end, and laid open the mischiefs our State hath long suffered by neglecting Fishing, which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> have made good use of to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves: I have made appear how easie it is to enrich our selves by it, and to restore our selves unto what we have lost, and shewed the profit all kinds of people may reap by it, if Will and Money be not wanting: I have made it plain to as many as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire the truth, that the increase of Shipping in <hi>Europe</hi> is occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the taking and transporting of our Fish, that 9000. <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Vessels are begot out of it, and all their people daily set on
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56259:22"/>work by it; insomuch as I dare boldly say, if the feeding upon Fish were prohibited all sorts of Christians, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand duly observed, it would lessen the number of Shipping three parts in five.</p>
               <p>And therefore, seeing that our <hi>Fish</hi> is able to make us happy, and this Narration laies down the way how to attain to that Happinesse, let neither Excuses, Calumniations, false pretences, or affection to the <hi>Hollanders</hi> divert us from it, as it did in the year 1609. when by Proclamation the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were bound to resort to the City of <hi>London</hi> for licence to fish upon the Coast of <hi>England,</hi> and to <hi>Edenburgh</hi> for the like liberty in <hi>Scotland,</hi> yet neither of these two things were performed, nor the Contempt questioned.</p>
               <p>Two hundred Usurers, with willing minds and forward pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, are able to master this work: but I fear the Devil will not allow them a Gain so well gotten. The excessive practice of Usurie is the decay of Commonwealths, repugnant to all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, Charity, and natural benevolence; and a slavery to themselves, who desire to live poor, and to die rich.</p>
               <p>But to speak truth, it is pity that a work of so great good and gain should have to doe with men of so penurious a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, who are neither good nor evil by the disposition of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but by their own perverse will and nature. God, I fear, will blesse our actions the worse for them, that are like trees that bear no blossoms in the Spring, and therefore no fruit at the Fall.</p>
               <p>This work is unspotted, and pittie it should be defiled with the sin of Avarice. His <hi>Majesties</hi> Greatnesse and Glory will appear by it: For nothing can be to a <hi>Prince</hi> more Royal and renowned, then to make the state of his Realm better then when he found it, and of idle and slothfull persons to make profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble members to a Commonwealth.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>